<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model
    href="https://vault.tei-c.org/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"
    schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
    type="application/xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">    
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Concerning Leif the Lucky from The Finding of Wineland the Good</title>
                <title type="sub">A Vinland Saga LOD project</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>compiled by</resp>
                    <persName ref="#RM">Regina Manyara</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Excerpted Digital Edition, <date when="2025-06">June, 2025</date> </edition>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>annotated by</resp>
                    <persName ref="#RM">Regina Manyara</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>
                <measure unit="kb" quantity="41">About 41KB</measure>
                <measure unit="lines" quantity="300">About 300 lines</measure>
            </extent>
            <publicationStmt> 
                <publisher>Alma Mater Studiorum - Università di Bologna</publisher>
                <pubPlace>
                    <placeName key="Bologna" sameAs="https://sws.geonames.org/3181928/">Bologna</placeName>
                </pubPlace>
                <date when="2025-06">June, 2025</date>
                <availability status="free"> 
                    <licence target= "https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"> CC-BY-NC</licence>
                    <p>Open Access. Available for academic purposes.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt> 
                <note>This is an XML/TEI document made for the DHDK exam of Information Science and Cultural Heritage (2024/25) 
                    as part of the LOD project VinLOD Saga.
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct xml:lang="en" type="print">
                    <monogr>
                        <title type="main">The Finding of Wineland the Good</title>
                        <title type="sub">The History of the Icelandic Discovery of America</title>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Edited and translated from the earliest records by</resp>
                            <persName ref="AMR">Author Middleton Reeves</persName>
                        </respStmt>
                        <note>With phototype plates of the Vellum MSS. of the sagas</note>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Henry Frowde Oxford University Press Warehouse Amen Corner, E.C.</publisher>
                            <date when="1890">1890</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                    <citedRange unit="page" from="35" to="38">pp 35-38</citedRange>
                </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:lang= "en" type="digital">
                    <monogr>
                        <idno type="internet_archive">findingofwinelan00reev</idno>
                        <idno type="open_library">OL24197049M</idno>
                        <idno type="URI">https://openlibrary.org/books/OL24197049M/The_finding_of_Wineland_the_Good</idno>
                        <title>The finding of Wineland the Good : the history of the Icelandic discovery of America, 
                            edited and translated from the earliest records</title>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>hosted by</resp>
                            <name>Internet Archive</name>
                        </respStmt>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="2010-04-27">27th April 2010</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <extent>1 online resource (vi, 205 pages :facs.)</extent>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <listWit>
                    <witness xml:id="EsR" source="https://handrit.is/manuscript/view/is/AM04-0557/0#mode/2up">AM. 557, 4to (Sögubók) - Saga of Erik the Red</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="THsK" source="https://handrit.is/manuscript/view/en/AM04-0544/0#mode/2up">AM. 544, 4to (Hauksbók) - Saga of Thorfinn Karlsefni</witness>
                </listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <variantEncoding method="location-referenced" location="external"/>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>
                    This digtal document is a part of the VinLOD Saga linked open data project for the DHDK exam of Information Science and Cultural Heritage (2024/25). For the Text Encoding and Semantic Representation part of the exam, this doucment was created to further enrich the details of the project. VinLOD Saga is inspired by and centred around the manga and anime series Vinland Saga by Makoto Yukimura, which have been connected to real world Norse cultural objects. Among these, are objects relating to Leif Eirikkson and his discovery of "Vinland" (North America). This document acts as an extention of these objects, transcribing and annotating the digital facsimile of "The Finding of Wineland the Good", a translated critical edition, by Arthur Middleton Reeves, of the Icelandic sagas related to the discovery of Vinland. In particular, the section "Concerning Leif the Lucky and the Introduction of Christianity into Greenland", within the tranlation of the "Saga of Erik the Red", was chosen for its direct, although small, mention of the Vinland discovery. 
                </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction status="low" method="silent">
                    <p>Errors in transcription controlled by using the VSCode extension <q>Code Spell Checker</q>. Errors which were present in the original text were left as is.</p>
                </correction>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Within the main text transcription, the <gi>seg</gi> element was used to further subdivide the smaller narratives within the main section of the saga.</p>
                    <p>Every person and place mentioned in the text has been marked once per small narrative segment. For people and places with no authoritive URI, a note has been added to their entry in <gi>listPerson</gi> and <gi>listPlace</gi>, respectively.</p>
                    <p>Dates are marked with the ISO 8601 date format, when possible.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization> 
                    <p>All words and letters are transcribed verbatim from the original, with no normalization applied, since the text was previously normalized by the author from Old Norse to Modern English (in archaic style).</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Spacing between words has been regularized to one space.</p>
                </normalization>
                <quotation marks="all">
                    <p>All quotation marks have been retained from the original text. For direct speech the element <gi>said</gi> with <att>aloud</att> set to true, was used inside the quotation marks. For indirect speech the same element was used with the <att>aloud</att> set to false.</p>
                </quotation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The text has been structured into three main sections. The <gi>front</gi>, which includes the Preface from the original text. The <gi>body</gi>, which includes the main text of the file, taken from a section of Chapter II. - The Saga of Erik the Red. This section has been further subdivided with <gi>seg</gi> marking the smaller acts within the main saga. The <gi>back</gi>, which includes all the endnotes related to the text present in the <gi>body</gi> section.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <listPerson type="contributor">
                    <person xml:id="RM" source="https://github.com/ValkyrieCain9">
                        <persName>Regina Manyara</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="AMR" source="https://lccn.loc.gov/n89602323">
                        <persName>Arthur Middleton Reeves</persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>    
                <listPerson type="character">
                    <person xml:id="ER" source="https://dbpedia.org/resource/Erik_the_Red">
                        <persName>Erik the Red</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="TH">
                        <persName>Thorhild(Thoihild)</persName>
                        <note>The wife of Erik the Red and mother of Leif Eirikson</note>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="LE" source="https://dbpedia.org/resource/Leif_Erikson" sameAs="https://w3id.org/vinLOD-saga/person/Leiv_Eiriksson"> 
                        <persName>Leif Eiriksson</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="TE" source="https://dbpedia.org/resource/Thorstein_Eiriksson">
                        <persName>Thorstein Eiriksson</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="OT" source="https://dbpedia.org/resource/Olaf_Tryggvason">
                        <persName>Olaf Tryggvason</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="TG">
                        <persName>Thorgunna</persName>
                        <note>The wife of Leif Eirikson</note>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="TB">
                        <persName>Thorbjorn</persName>
                        <note>The father of Gudrid</note>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="GT" source="https://dbpedia.org/resource/Gudrid_Thorbjarnard%C3%B3ttir">
                        <persName>Gudrid Thorbjarnardóttir</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="TK" source="https://dbpedia.org/resource/Thorfinn_Karlsefni">
                        <persName>Thorfinn Karlsefni</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="TD">
                        <persName>Thurid</persName>
                        <note>The lady of the Fróda farm</note>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
            </particDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <listPlace>
                    <place xml:id="VL" sameAs="https://w3id.org/vinLOD-saga/place/Vinland">
                        <placeName>Vinland</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="GL" source="https://sws.geonames.org/3425505/">
                        <placeName>Greenland</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="NO" source="https://sws.geonames.org/3144096/">
                        <placeName>Norway</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="HB" source="https://sws.geonames.org/2647204/">
                        <placeName>Hebrides</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="IL" source="https://sws.geonames.org/2629691/">
                        <placeName>Iceland</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="BT" source="https://sws.geonames.org/3420741/">
                        <placeName>Brattahlid</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="EF">
                        <placeName>Ericsfirth</placeName>
                        <note>Leif Eirikson's home in Greenland</note>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="SF" source="https://sws.geonames.org/3413200/">
                        <placeName>Snæfellsnes</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="SH" source="https://sws.geonames.org/3413453/">
                        <placeName>Skálholt</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="FR" source="https://nat.is/froda/">
                        <placeName>Fródá</placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="preface">
                <head rend="align(center) case(allcaps)">Preface.</head>
                <p>
                    <!-- Page v — (9/280) -->
                    A <span rend ="case(allcaps)">chapter</span> title in the Codex Frisianus, '<foreign xml:lang="is">Fundit Vínland góða</foreign>' [Wineland the Good found], which has been reproduced in enlarged facsimile on the cover, has suggested the title for this book. The chapter which this title heads will be found on page 14. The Icelandic text there cited has been copied directly from the original, and this method has also been pursued in the other cases where citations of strictly historical matter have been made. In printing these citations, accents, punctuation and capital letters have been added, and supplied contractions have been printed in italics. Passages which have not been regarded as clearly historical have also been given in the original, but in this case it has been deemed sufficient to print after the best published texts. Icelandic proper names, where they occur in the translations, have been somewhat altered from their correct form, to the end that they might appear less strange to the English reader. This liberty has been taken with less hesitancy since it has been possible to give these names in their proper forms in the Index.
                </p>
                <p>
                    To the kindness of Dr. Bruun, Librarian of the Royal Library of Copenhagen, I am indebted for the privilege which has made the photographic reproduction of the Wineland History of the Flatey Book possible. I am under like obligation to the Arna-Magnæan Legation for the use, for a similar purpose, of the manuscripts AM.<note n="1" place="bottom">This contraction is used throughout to describe the manuscripts belonging to the Arna-Magnæan Collection.</note> 557 4to and 544 410. To one member of the Arna-Magnæan Legation, Dr. Kristian Kålund, I am under still further obligation for very many favours, which his profound acquaintance with 
                    
                    <!-- Page vi — (10/280) -->
                    Icelandic manuscripts, and especially with those in his charge as Librarian of the Arna-Magnæan Library, have rendered particularly valuable. To Professor Gustav Storm I feel myself peculiarly indebted for the kindly help, which he so freely tendered me at a time when the courtesy was extended at the expense of his own personal engagements. My thanks are also due to Dr. Finnur Jónsson, for his supervision of the photographing of the Arna-Magnæan manuscripts, and for other friendly acts. I am likewise under obligation to Captain Holm, of the Danish Navy, and Captain Phythian, of the United States Navy, for help, which finds more particular mention elsewhere. Finally and especially, I owe to Dr. <foreign xml:lang="is">Valtýr Guðmundsson</foreign> an expression of the appreciation I feel for his frequent and ever ready assistance, and particularly for his review of the proofs of the Icelandic texts.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The kindness which these friends have shown me has contributed in no small degree to the pleasure which the making of these pages has afforded.
                </p>
                <p rend="align(right)">
                    <persName ref="#AMR">A. M. R.</persName>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Berlin, <date when="1890-07"><span rend="italic">July</span>, 1890.</date>
                </p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <note type="editor">The following transcription is taken from a section of Chapter II. - The Saga of Erik the Red</note>
            <div type="translation">
                <head rend="align(center) case(allcaps)">Concerning Leif the Lucky and the Introduction of Christianity into Greenland.</head>
                <p>
                    <!-- page 35 (47/280) -->
                    <seg xml:id="intro"><persName ref="#ER">Eric</persName> was married to a woman named <span n="1">Thorhild</span> and had two sons; one of these was named <persName ref="#TE">Thorstein</persName>, and the other <persName ref="#LE">Leif</persName>. They were both promising men. Thorstein lived at home with his father, and there was not at that time a man in <placeName ref="#GL">Greenland</placeName> who was accounted of so great promise as he. Leif had sailed <note place="end" target="#n-32">(32)</note> to <placeName ref="#NO">Norway</placeName>, where he was at the court of King <persName ref="#OT">Olaf Tryggvason</persName>.</seg>

                    <seg xml:id="thorgunna">When <persName ref="#LE">Leif</persName> sailed from <placeName ref="#GL">Greenland</placeName>, in the summer, they were driven out of their course to the <placeName ref="#HB">Hebrides</placeName>. It was late before they got fair winds thence, and they remained there far into the summer. Leif became enamoured of a certain woman, whose name was <persName ref="#TG">Thorgunna</persName>. She was a woman of fine family, and Leif observed that she was possessed of <span n="2">rare intelligence</span> <note place="end" target="#n-33">(33)</note>. When Leif was preparing for his departure Thorgunna <note place="end" target="#n-34">(34)</note> asked to be permitted to accompany him. Leif enquired <said aloud="false" who="#LE">whether she had in this the approval of her kinsmen</said>. She replied that <said aloud="false" who="#TG">she did not care for it</said>. Leif responded that <said aloud="false" who="#LE">he did not deem it the part of wisdom to abduct so high-born a woman in a strange country</said>, '<said aloud="true" who="#LE">and we so few in number</said>.' '<said aloud="true" who="#TG">It is by no means certain that thou
                    
                    <!-- Page 36 (48/280) -->
                    shall find this to be the better decision</said>,' said Thorgunna. '<said aloud="true" who="#LE">I shall put it to the proof, notwithstanding</said>,' said Leif. '<said aloud="true" who="#TG">Then I tell thee</said>,' said Thorgunna, '<said aloud="true" who="#TG">that I am no longer a lone woman, for I am pregnant, and upon thee I charge it. I foresee that I shall give birth to a male child. And though thou give this no heed, yet will I rear the boy, and send him to thee in <placeName ref="#GL">Greenland</placeName>, when he shall be fit to take his place with other men. And I foresee that thou wilt get as much profit of this son as is thy due from this our parting; moreover, I mean to come to Greenland myself before the end comes</said>.' Leif gave her a gold finger-ring, a Greenland wadmal mantle, and a belt of walrus-tusk. This boy came to Greenland, and was called Thorgils. Leif acknowledged his paternity, and some men will have it that this Thorgils came to <placeName ref="#IL">Iceland</placeName> in the summer before the <placeName ref="#FR">Fródá</placeName>-wonder <note place="end" target="#n-35">(35)</note>. However, this Thorgils was afterwards in Greenland, and there seemed to be something not altogether natural about him before the end came.</seg> 
                    
                    <seg xml:id="tryggvason"><persName ref="#LE">Leif</persName> and his companions sailed away from the <placeName ref="#HB">Hebrides</placeName>, and arrived in <placeName ref="#NO">Norway</placeName> in the autumn. Leif went to the court of King <persName ref="#OT">Olaf Tryggvason</persName>. He was well received by the king, who felt that he could see that Leif was a man of great accomplishments. Upon one occasion the king came to speech with Leif, and asks him, '<said aloud="true" who="#OT">Is it thy purpose to sail to <placeName ref="#GL">Greenland</placeName> in the summer</said>?' '<said aloud="true" who="#LE">It is my purpose</said>,' said Leif, '<said aloud="true" who="#LE">if it be your will</said>.' '<said aloud="true" who="#OT">I believe it will be well</said>,' answers the king, '<said aloud="true" who="#OT">and thither thou shalt go upon my errand, to proclaim Christianity there</said>.' Leif replied that <said aloud="false" who="#LE">the king should decide, but gave it as his belief that it would be difficult to carry this mission to a successful issue in Greenland</said>. The king replied that <said aloud="false" who="#LE">he knew of no man who would be better fitted for this undertaking</said>, '<said aloud="true" who="#OT">and in thy hands the cause will surely prosper</said>.' '<said aloud="true" who="#LE">This can only be</said>,' said Leif, '<said aloud="true" who="#LE">if I enjoy the grace of your protection</said>.'</seg>
                    
                    <seg xml:id="vinland"><persName ref="#LE">Leif</persName> put to sea when his ship was ready for the voyage. For a long time he was tossed about upon the ocean, and came upon <placeName ref="#VL">lands</placeName> of which he had previously had no knowledge. There were self-sown wheat fields and vines growing there. There were also those trees there which are called 'mausur' <note place="end" target="#n-36">(36)</note>, and of all these they took specimens. Some of the timbers were so large that they were used in building. Leif found men upon a wreck, and took them home with him, and procured quarters for them all during the winter. In this wise he showed his nobleness and goodness, since he introduced Christianity into the country, and saved the men from the <span n="3">wreck</span>; and he was called <span n="4">Leif the Lucky</span> - ever after.</seg> 
                    
                    <seg xml:id="christianity"><persName ref="#LE">Leif</persName> landed in <placeName ref="#EF">Ericsfirth</placeName>, and then went home to <placeName ref="#BT">Brattahlid</placeName>; he was well received by every one. He soon proclaimed Christianity throughout the land, and the Catholic faith, and announced King <persName ref="#OT">Olaf Tryggvason</persName>'s messages to the people, telling them how much excellence and how great glory accompanied this faith. <persName ref="#ER">Eric</persName> was slow in
                    
                    <!-- Page 37 (49/280) -->
                    forming the determination to forsake his old belief, but <persName ref="#TH">Thiodhild</persName> <note place="end" target="#n-37">(37)</note> embraced the faith promptly, and caused a church to be built at some distance from the house. This building was called Thiodhild's Church, and there she and those persons who had accepted Christianity, and they were many, were wont to offer their prayers. Thiodhild would not have intercourse with Eric after that she had received the faith, whereat he was sorely vexed.</seg>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <seg xml:id="preparation">At this time there began to be much talk about a voyage of <span n="5">exploration</span> to that <placeName ref="#VL">country</placeName> which <persName ref="#LE">Leif</persName> had discovered. The leader of this expedition was <persName ref="#TE">Thorstein Ericsson</persName>, who was a good man and an intelligent, and blessed with many friends. <persName ref="#ER">Eric</persName> was likewise invited to join them, for the men believed that his luck and foresight would be of great furtherance. He was slow in deciding, but did not say nay, when his friends besought him to go. They thereupon equipped that ship in which <persName ref="#TB">Thorbiorn</persName> had come out, and twenty men were selected for the expedition. They took little cargo with them, nought else save their <span n="6">weapons and provisions</span>.</seg> 
                    
                    <seg xml:id="fall">On that morning when <persName ref="#ER">Eric</persName> set out from his home he took with him a little chest containing gold and silver; he hid this treasure, and then went his way. He had proceeded but a short distance, however, when he fell from his horse and broke his ribs and dislocated his <span n="7">shoulder</span>, whereat he cried <span n="8">'Ai, ai!'</span> By reason of this accident <span n="9">he sent his wife word</span> that she should procure the treasure which he had concealed, for to the hiding of the treasure he attributed his misfortune <note place="end" target="#n-38">(38)</note>.</seg> 
                    
                    <seg xml:id="failure">Thereafter they sailed cheerily out of <placeName ref="#EF">Ericsfirth</placeName> in high spirits over their plan. They were long tossed about upon the ocean, and could not lay the course they wished. They came in sight of <placeName ref="#IL">Iceland</placeName>, and likewise saw birds from the Irish coast<note n="10" place="bottom">Lit.'had birds from Ireland;' that is, came near enough to the coast of Ireland to see land birds.</note>. Their ship was, in sooth, driven hither and thither over the sea. In the autumn they turned back, worn out by toil, and exposure to the elements, and exhausted by their labours, and arrived at Ericsfirth at the very beginning of winter.  Then said <persName ref="#ER">Eric</persName>, '<said aloud="true" who="#ER">More cheerful were <span n="11">we</span> in the summer, when we put out of the firth, but we still live<note n="12" place="bottom">Lit. 'but now we are'</note>, and it might have been much worse<note n="13" place="bottom">Lit. 'and there is still much good left;' that is, we have still much to be grateful for</note></said>.' <persName ref="#TE">Thorstein</persName> answers, '<said aloud="true" who="#ER">It will be a princely deed to endeavour to look well after the wants of all these men who are now in need, and to make provision for them during the winter.</said>' Eric answers, '<said aloud="true" who="#ER">It is ever true, as it is said, that "it is never clear ere the answer comes," and so it 
                            
                    <!-- Page 38 (50/280) -->      
                    must be here. We will act now upon thy counsel in this <span n="14">matter</span></said>. 'All of the men, who were not otherwise provided for, accompanied the father and son. They landed thereupon, and went home to Brattahlid, where they remained throughout the winter.</seg>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <listApp>
                    <app loc="1">
                        <rdg wit="#EsR">Thiodhild</rdg>
                    </app>
                    <app loc="2">
                        <rdg wit="#EsR">lit. 'knew more than a little'</rdg>
                    </app>
                    <app loc="3">
                        <rdg wit="#EsR">'as in many other ways, for he brought Christianity to the country'</rdg>
                    </app>
                    <app loc="4">
                        <rdg wit="#EsR">hinn heppni</rdg>
                    </app>
                    <app loc="5">
                        <rdg wit="#EsR">'From this there began to be much talk, that he should explore'</rdg>
                    </app>
                    <app loc="6">
                        <rdg wit="#EsR">'mostly weapons and provisions'</rdg>
                    </app>
                    <app loc="7">
                        <rdg wit="#THsK">'injured his arm at the shoulder-joint'</rdg>
                    </app>
                    <app loc="8">
                        <rdg wit="#THsK" type="ommison">Ommited</rdg>
                    </app>
                    <app loc="9">
                        <rdg wit="#THsK">lit. 'he told his wife'</rdg>
                    </app>
                    <app loc="11">
                        <rdg wit="#EsR">has 'ye' instead of 'we' throughout</rdg>
                    </app>
                    <app loc="14">
                        <rdg wit="#EsR">'Eric answers, " These words shall control here." All of those, who had not been provided for before, [obtained] accommodation with Eric and his son'</rdg>
                        <note>The passage, apparently by reason of a clerical confusion, is not clear without emendation</note>
                    </app>
                </listApp>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="endnotes">
                <head rend="align(center) case(allcaps)">Notes.</head>
                <noteGrp>
                    <note xml:id="n-32">
                        <p>
                            (32) The expression '<persName ref="#LE">Leif</persName> had sailed' ['<foreign xml:lang="is">Leifr hafði siglt</foreign>'], would seem to refer to an antecedent condition, possibly to the statement concerning the arrival of <persName ref="#TB">Thorbiorn</persName> and his daughter at <placeName ref="#BT">Brattahlid</placeName>; i.e. 'Leif had sailed,' when they arrived. If this be, indeed, the fact, it follows that Thorbiorn and his daughter must have arrived at Brattahlid during Leif's absence in <placeName ref="#NO">Norway</placeName>, and obviously before his return to <placeName ref="#GL">Greenland</placeName>, in the autumn of the <date when="1000">year 1000</date>. Upon this hypothesis, it is clear, that Thorbiorn and <persName ref="#GT">Gudrid</persName> must have been converted to Christianity before its legal acceptance in <placeName ref="#IL">Iceland</placeName>, that is to say, before the year 1000; and further, that <persName ref="#TE">Thorstein Ericsson</persName> may have been married to Gudrid in the autumn after his return from his unsuccessful voyage, namely, in the autumn of the <date when="1001">year 1001</date>; accordingly <persName ref="#TK">Karlsefni</persName> may have arrived in the following year, have been wedded to Gudrid at the next Yule-tide, <date from="1002-12" to="1003-01">1002–3</date>, and have undertaken his voyage to Wineland in the <date when="1003">year 1003</date>. This chronology is suggested with the sole aim of fixing the earliest possible date for Karlsefni's voyage of exploration.
                        </p>
                    </note>
                    <note xml:id="n-33">
                        <p>
                            (33) The expression of ÞsK. 'margkunnig,' conveys the impression that <persName ref="#TG">Thorgunna</persName> was gifted with preternatural wisdom.
                        </p>
                    </note>
                    <note xml:id="n-34">
                        <p>
                            <!-- Page 168 (236/280) -->
                            (34) It has been suggested, that this Thorgunna is the same woman of whom we read in the Eyrbyggja Saga: <seg xml:id="thorgunna-eyrbyggja">'That summer, when Christianity was accepted by law in <placeName ref="#IL">Iceland</placeName>, a ship arrived out by <placeName ref="#SF">Snowfells-ness</placeName>; this was a Dublin ship...There was a woman of the <placeName ref="#HB">Hebrides</placeName> on board, whose name was <persName ref="#TG">Thorgunna</persName>; the ship's folk reported, that she had brought with her such precious articles as were very rare in <placeName ref="#IL">Iceland</placeName>. And when <persName ref="#TD">Thurid</persName>, the mistress of <placeName ref="#FR">Fródá</placeName>, heard this, she was very curious to see these treasures; for she was fond of finery, and showy in her dress; she accordingly went to the ship, where she met Thorgunna, and enquired of her whether she had any woman's garb of surpassing beauty. <persName ref="#TG">She</persName> replied, that <said aloud="false" who="#TG">she had no precious things to sell, but that she had finery in which she felt it no disgrace to appear at feasts or other assemblies</said>. Thurid asked to see these articles, and was well pleased with them, and thought them very becoming, but not of very great value. Thurid endeavoured to purchase these articles, but Thorgunna would not sell them. Thereupon Thurid invited her to make her home with her, for she knew that Thorgunna had many treasures, and she thought that, sooner or later, she might succeed in obtaining them. Thorgunna replies: "<said aloud="true" who="#TG">I am well content to make my home with thee, but thou shalt know that I am inclined to give but little for my maintenance, since I am well able to work; wherefore I will myself decide what I shall give for my support from such property as I possess</said>." Thorgunna spoke about the matter somewhat harshly, but Thurid still insisted that she should accompany her. Thorgunna's belongings were then carried from the ship; they were contained in a large locked chest and a portable box; these were carried to Fródá, and when Thorgunna came to her lodgings, she asked to be provided with a bed, and a place was assigned her in the innermost part of the sleeping-apartment. She then unlocked her chest, and took from it bed-clothes, which were all very elaborately wrought; she spread an English sheet and silk quilt over the bed; she took bed-curtains from the chest together with all the precious hangings of a bed; all of these were so fine that the folk thought they had never seen the like. Thereupon Mistress Thurid exclaimed: "<said aloud="true" who="#TD">Fix a price upon the bed-clothing</said>." Thorgunna replies: "<said aloud="true" who="#TG">I shall not lie in straw for thee, even if thou art fine-mannered and carriest thyself proudly</said>." Thurid was displeased at this, and did not again seek to obtain the precious articles. Thorgunna worked at weaving every day, when there was no hay-making; but when the weather was dry, she worked at hay-making in the in-fields, and she had a rake made especially for her, and would use no other. Thorgunna  
                                
                            <!-- Page 169 (237/280) -->
                            was a large woman, tall, and very stout; with dark brown eyes set close together, and thick brown hair; she was for the most part pleasant in her bearing, attended church every morning before she went to her work, but was not, as a rule, easy of approach nor inclined to be talkative. It was the common opinion that Thorgunna must be in the sixties.' [Eyrbyggja Saga, ed. Vigfusson, pp. 92-3.] In the autumn after her arrival Thorgunna died, and the strange events accompanying her last illness, are recorded in the chapter following that above quoted. As she approached her end, she called the master of the house to her, and said: '"<said aloud="true" who="#TG">It is my last wish, if I die from this illness, that my body be conveyed to <placeName ref="#SH">Skálholt</placeName>, for I foresee that it is destined to be one of the most famous spots in this land, and I know that there must be priests there now to chant my funeral service. I would, therefore, request thee to have my body conveyed thither, for which thou shalt have suitable compensation from my possessions; while of my undivided property Thurid shall receive the scarlet cloak, and I thus direct, that she may be content, if I make such disposition of my other property as I see fit; moreover, I would have thee requite thyself for such expense as thou hast incurred in my behalf, with such articles as thou wishest, or she may choose, of that which I so appoint. I have a gold ring, which is to go with my body to the church, but my bed and hangings I wish to have burned, for these will not be of profit to any one; and this I say, not because I would deprive any one of the use of these things, if I believed that they would be useful; but I dwell so particularly upon this," says she, "because I should regret, that so great affliction should be visited upon any one, as I know must be, if my wishes should not be fulfilled</said>."' [Eyrbyggja Saga, 1. c. pp. 95-6.]</seg>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            The age here assigned to <persName ref="#TG">Thorgunna</persName> hardly agrees with the probable age of the Hebridean Thorgunna of Leif's acquaintance. Indeed the description of this remarkable woman, as given in 'Eyrbyggja,' would seem to indicate that there may have been an error in the age there assigned her, possibly a clerical error; if this is not the fact, it is pretty clear, that the Hebridean Thorgunna of <persName ref="#LE">Leif</persName>'s acquaintance and the Thorgunna of 'Eyrbyggja' cannot be the same person. We are given to understand in the Saga of Eric the Red, that the woman of Leif's intrigue was a woman out of the ordinary rank; we are also told, that Leif gave her many precious bits of finery, among the rest a gold ring, and a mantle of wadmal. The Thorgunna of 'Eyrbyggja' was certainly an extraordinary woman, and was distinguished also for the apparel and ornaments which she possessed. The parallelism is sufficiently striking to point to the possibility, that the Thorgunna of 'Eyrbyggja' was the Thorgunna of Eric's Saga, who had, perhaps, come to <placeName ref="#IL">Iceland</placeName> to seek a passage to <placeName ref="#GL">Greenland</placeName>, in pursuance of her intention as announced to Leif at their parting. It is stated in Eric's Saga to have been rumoured, that Thorgunna's son came to Iceland in the summer before the <placeName ref="#FR">Fródá</placeName>-wonder. The Thorgunna of the Eyrbyggja Saga arrived in Iceland the summer before this 'wonder,' which indeed, owed its origin to her coming, but there is no mention in this saga of her having had a son, a singular omission, truly, if it be an omission, in so minute a description as the saga has preserved of this remarkable woman. Finally, it is evident, if Leif's voyage to <placeName ref="#NO">Norway</placeName> was made in <date when="0999">999</date>, and the Thorgunna of Leif's intrigue and she of 'Eyrbyggja' are the same, that Thorgunna's son must have been of a very tender age at the time of his mother's arrival in Iceland. In view of these, as well as certain chronological difficulties, which this narrative presents, it seems not improbable that the whole account of 
                            
                            <!-- Page 170 (238/280) -->
                            Thorgunna and the Fródá-wonder, as contained in 'Eyrbyggja,' was a popular tale interjected in the saga for a reason not now apparent. This tale may well have been builded upon a historical foundation, but the remains of this foundation are not sufficiently well-preserved to enable us to separate accurately the sound from the unsound material<note place="bottom">Cf. Vigfusson, Eyrbyggja Saga, Vorrede, p. xvii.</note>.
                        </p>
                    </note>
                    <note xml:id="n-35">
                        <p>
                            (35) The <placeName ref="#FR">Fródá</placeName>-wonder is the name given to the extraordinary occurrences, which befell at the farmstead of Fródá soon after <persName ref="#TG">Thorgunna</persName>'s death. The 'wonder' began with the appearance of a 'weird-moon,' which was supposed to betoken the death of some member of the family. This baleful prophecy was followed by the death of eighteen members of the household, and subsequently by the nightly apparitions of the dead. The cause of this marvel was attributed to the fact, that the <persName ref="#TD">Mistress of Fródá</persName> had prevailed upon her husband to disregard Thorgunna's injunction to burn the drapery of her bed; and not until these hangings were burned was the evil influence exorcised, and the ghostly apparitions laid, the complete restoration of the normal condition of affairs being further facilitated by the timely recommendations of a priest, whose services had been secured to that end.<note place="bottom">Cf. Eyrbyggja Saga, ed. Vigfusson, pp. 98-102.</note>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                    <note xml:id="n-36">
                        <p>
                            (36) It is not certain what variety of wood is meant; the generally accepted view has been, that it was some species of maple. It has also been suggested that the word mausurr mǫsurr, may be allied to the modern Swedish Masbjörk, veined-birch, German, Maser-birke, and again [cf. Grönl. hist. Mindesm. vol. i. p. 280] to the German Meussdorn, a view which Arngrim Jonsson was the first to advance [Gronlandia, ch. x]. It was believed, that this last-named received its name, '<foreign xml:lang="de">darumb das diser dorn den Meusen und ratten zu wider ist</foreign>,' [Bock, Kreuter Buch, ch. cxliij]. The same author writes of this wood: '<foreign xml:lang="de">ist man fro das man Meussdorn zu Besen bekommen kan, als zu Venedig vnd sunst auf den Meerstetten. Die Meuss vnd Ratten werden mit disen dornen verscheucht</foreign>' [Hieronymus Bock [Tragus], Kreuter Buch, 1546, p. 347]. It may be, that this or a similar passage suggested to Finn Magnusen and Werlauff the interpretation, 'besom,' 'broom,' which they gave to húsasnotra [af mǫsurtré ; cf note 6]. That the tree called mǫsurr was also indigenous in Norway is in a manner confirmed by a passage in the Short Story of Helgi Thorisson [Þáttr Helga Þórissonar], contained in Flatey Book [vol. i. p. 359]: 'One summer these brothers engaged in a trading voyage to Finmark in the north, having butter and pork to sell to the Finns. They had a successful trading expedition, and returned when the summer was far-spent, and came by day to a cape called Vimund. There were very excellent woods here. They went ashore, and obtained some "mǫsurr" wood.' The character of this narrative, and the locality assigned to the 'mǫsurr' trees, affect the trustworthiness of the information. It is reasonably clear, however, that the wood was rare and, whether it grew in Finmark or not, it was evidently highly prized<note place="bottom">Cf. Saga Haralds harðráða, Fornmannasögur, vol.vi. p. 184.</note>. 
                        </p>
                    </note>
                    <note xml:id="n-37">
                        <p>
                            (37) <persName ref="#TH">Thiodhild</persName> is also called Thorhild, and similarly <persName ref="#GT">Gudrid</persName> is called Thurid. It has been conjectured, that Thorhild and Thurid were the earlier names, which were changed by their owners after their conversion to Christianity, because of the suggestion of the heathen god in the first syllable of their original names.<note place="bottom">Cf. Grönl. hist. Mindesm. vol. i. 256-7, 471.</note>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                    <note xml:id="n-38">
                        <p>
                            (38) Such a fall as this of <persName ref="#ER">Eric</persName>'s does not seem to have been generally regarded as an evil omen, if we may be guided by the proverb: '<foreign xml:lang="is">Fall er farar heill</foreign>' [Óláfs saga Trjyggvasonar, Flateyjarbók. 1. c. vol. i. p. 231]. The complete saying is given by Guðmundr Jónsson [Safn af Ífslenzkum Orðskviðum, Copenh. 1830. p. 100]: '<foreign xml:lang="is">Fall er fararheill frá garði en ei í garð</foreign>,' 'a fall bodes a lucky journey from the house but not toward it.'
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </noteGrp>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>